Rhiannon: There has been a fundamental
shift in the attitude of society to
being more aware and accepting of
those with mental health problems.
Common mental disorders such as
depression and anxiety are discussed
more openly, and people are more willing
to seek help if they feel affected.
Today individuals who have been affected
by childhood trauma are more likely to
talk about it than in the past and society
is more aware of its potential causes.
High profile cases of childhood abuse
have helped to highlight cases both in
popular culture and sporting circles
to make this all the more possible.
Innovation in digital systems,
digital and social media have helped
bring mental health issues to the
fingertips of everyone supplying an
unlimited amount of information and
websites to further our knowledge and
understanding of mental health in general.
New ideas such as mindfulness, and the
use of tried and tested techniques such as
yoga and meditation can help make people
aware of their own mental health and more
readily appreciate the problems of others.
However, there is still social
stigma associated with mental health.
Many people with mental health problems
say that social stigma and discrimination
have had a negative effect on their lives.
This is because society in general
still has a stereotypical view on mental
illness and how it affects people.
Some people still believe those who suffer
from mental ill health, could be violent
or dangerous when in fact they are more
likely to suffer from violence themselves.
The situation is made worse when
the media portray people with
mental health problems as dangerous,
criminal, evil, or disabled and unable
to live normal, fulfilled lives.
Most aspects of mental illness and
psychological well‐being are influenced
by social factors such as gender,
social class, race and ethnicity.
A persons cultural background
can impact on attitudes to mental
health on several different levels.
Knowledge, attitudes and behaviours
from different social and
cultural groups are not the same.
For some ethnic groups mental illness is
a taboo subject, and there is little open
discussion about mental health problems.
In some communities, caring for a child or
young person with a mental health problem
is seen as a family responsibility.
Diagnoses are something to be kept
private and not openly discussed, even
with immediate family and this is partly
down to the need to preserve the family’s
reputation and status at all costs.
Children and young people from
different ethnic or cultural groups
may have a higher risk of mental health
problems because they may experience
a greater number of stressors, such
as discrimination and isolation.
They may also feel split between
two communities, and therefore
feel torn between the different
social and cultural attitudes.
This can be more of an issue when gender
is brought into the equation, with
girls much more likely to be affected
than boys as equality of gender is
not as prevalent in all communities.
Shame, fear and secrecy surrounds
mental illness as the causes
are often misunderstood.
In some communities, children and
young people with mental health
problems are not valued, for example,
marriage prospects can be damaged
by perceptions of mental illness.
The culture of secrecy that surrounds
mental illness can, in part, be attributed
to misunderstandings and misconceptions
that have grown up around all aspects of
mental health problems over many years.
However, on the whole the younger
generations generally have better
attitudes to mental health problems
than older age groups and will speak
about mental health problems more
openly among themselves in all cultures.
So, in this vein, hopefully we continue
to see this increased positive trend
and work towards eradicating the
misconceptions and stigma over time.